Finding Aid for Oscar Gottlieb Christgau Papers, 1908-1971
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Oscar Gottlieb Christgau Papers 1908-1971
Christgau, Oscar Gottlieb.
85988 Aa 2; AC; UAl
Temperance leader, assistant to the general superintendent of the Anti-Saloon League of America. Correspondence, scrapbooks, dramatic productions, photographs, and printed material concerning the enforcement and repeal of the 18th Amendment, the political activities of the Anti-Saloon League, particularly during the election of 1928, and the temperance activities of William Jennings Bryan, Morris Sheppard, Billy Sunday, and F. Scott McBride. Correspondents include: Patrick H. Callahan, James Cannon, Arthur Capper, Luren D. Dickinson, F. Scott McBride, Homer Rodeheaver, Howard H. Russell, Morris.
12.2 linear feet
2 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mr. Christgau (donor no. 4853 ) and came to the library in 1970. Additional accessions were received.
The collection is open to research.
Oscar Gottlieb Christgau was actively involved in the temperance movement in the United States for more than fifty years. He began, in 1915, as a speaker for the Anti-Saloon League of Illinois and was later appointed editor of the Illinois Edition of The American Issue, the Anti-Saloon League newspaper. It was in Illinois that Christgau began working with F. Scott McBride, who was then state ASL Superintendent. Christgau became his assistant and continued to speak, write, and organize upon behalf of the prohibition amendment. When McBride took on the position of national ASL General Superintendent in 1924, Christgau followed him as Assistant National Superintendent. For the next two decades, throughout the Twenties and Thirties, he worked tirelessly for the League and its policies. In the Twenties, he continually urged fall enforcement of the 18th Amendment; and then, in the Thirties, after the amendment had been repealed, he urged the passage of prohibition laws within local communities.
As assistant to McBride, Christgau had many responsibilities. He was manager of the national and regional conventions of the ASL. He supervised all of the necessary local arrangements, arranged for speakers, and coordinated the convention schedules. Christgau was also in charge of the ASL's National Speaker's Bureau. In this capacity, he sought out nationally prominent speakers willing to preach the gospel of temperance to conferences and local churches. Such speakers included Billy Sunday, World War I hero Alvin York, and temperance stalwart Sam Morris.
Christgau was a pioneer in the use of temperance dramas as a vehicle for gaining converts to the cause. Among others, he authored a dramatic debate entitled, "Can the Law Be Enforced?" and a play "Senator North's Deciding Vote." Christgau appeared in many of these productions himself.
In 1942, Christgau was elected State Superintendent of the Iowa ASL. This was to be his last full-time temperance position.
The Christgau Collection is comprised of correspondence, scrapbooks, topical files, printed matter, and photographs covering the period of roughly 1906 to 1971. The Correspondence deals largely with the mechanics of Christgau's work: the enlisting and scheduling of temperance speeches and productions, local arrangements for temperance conventions, and personal support for local option and other temperance-related issues. Though there is some overlap, the collection includes a separate series of correspondence and other materials relating specifically to his work as manager of the regional Southeastern Conference convention of the ASL which met each year in St. Petersburg, Florida. This sequence of correspondence covers the years 1928 to 1948.
The collection includes Christgau's autobiography, many of his speeches and notes for speeches, notes which he made on the conventions he managed and the speeches he heard, and copies of the addresses he made over the radio in the late Thirties and throughout the 1940's. Christgau also maintained separate files documenting his work with the national ASL and the ASL of Illinois, Iowa, and Minnesota. In a series of topical files, Christgau included information, clippings, and printed materials on individuals associated with the temperance movement and with issues of concern to temperance groups.
The collection also contains files pertaining to the dramatic productions which Christgau presented under ASL auspices. These files have been arranged by the name of the production and include texts of the drama and promotional materials. The remainder of the collection consists of a section of temperance printed items, newspaper clippings, bound scrapbooks and photographs.
Subjects:
Anti-Saloon League of America.; Bryan, William Jennings, 1860-1925.; Christgau, Oscar Gottlieb.; Presidents--United States--Election--1928.; Prohibition--United States.; Social reformers--United States.; Temperance--United States.; United States--Politics and government--1923-1929.; United States--Politics and government--1933-1945.; United States--Politics and government--1929-1933.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Anti-Saloon League of America.; Bryan, William Jennings, 1860-1925.; Christgau, Oscar Gottlieb.; McBride, Francis Scott, 1872-1955.; Prohibition--United States.; Rodeheaver, Homer A. (Homer Alvan), 1880-1955.; Sheppard, Morris, 1875-1941.; Temperance--United States.; York, Alvin Cullum, 1887-1964.
Contributors:
Callahan, Patrick Henry, 1866-1940.; Cannon, James, 1864-1944.; Capper, Arthur, 1865-1951.; Dickinson, Luren Dudley, 1859-1943.; McBride, Francis Scott, 1872-1955.; Rodeheaver, Homer A. (Homer Alvan), 1880-1955.; Russell, Howard H. (Howard Hyde), 1855-1946.; Sheppard, Morris, 1875-1941.; Sunday, Billy, 1862-1935.; Wallace, Clayton Morey, 1897-; York, Alvin Cullum, 1887-1964.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Biographical/personal
  - Autobiography: "Adventures of a Dry Crusader" (Box 1)
  - Personal and biographical material (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Undated 1906-1937, 48 folders (Box 1)
  - 1938-1943, 44 folders (Box 2)
  - 1944-1971, 46 folders (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous notes
  - Notes (miscellaneous) undated, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Notes (miscellaneous) 1920-1921 (Box 4)
- Speeches, writings, and related
  - Poetry (Box 4)
  - Speeches and speech notes undated, 6 folders (Box 4)
  - Speech notes, ca. 1909-1910, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Speech notes 1914-1962 (Box 4)
  - Notes on temperance conventions and speeches, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Notices of Christgau speeches and related correspondence (Box 4)
  - Papers relating to speaking engagements and the scheduling of speeches, ca. 1933, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Radio addresses
    - Undated (Box 4)
    - 1924, 1931, 1939, 1944 (Box 4)
    - January-March 1945 (Box 4)
    - April-June 1945 (Box 4)
    - July-September 1945 (Box 4)
    - October-December 1945 (Box 4)
    - 1946 1948 (Box 4)
  - Articles and other writings (Box 4)
- Anti-Saloon League of America. Southeastern Conference
  - St. Petersburg Convention files
    - Undated and miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - 1928, 1931, 1932, 1938, 1939 (Box 5)
    - 1940 meeting, 6 folders (Box 5)
    - 1941 meeting, 5 folders (Box 5)
    - 1942 meeting, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - 1943 meeting, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1944 meeting, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1945 meeting, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - 1946 meeting, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - 1947 meeting, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1948 meeting, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - National Conventions
    - 1916 1932-1939 (Box 5)
    - 1940 (Box 5)
    - 1943 (Box 5)
    - 1944 (Box 5)
    - 1946 (miscellaneous) (Box 5)
    - 1946 (correspondence), 4 folders (Box 5)
    - 1948 (miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - 1948 (correspondence), 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Convention miscellanea (Box 5)
- Anti-Saloon League of America files
  - Weekly reports of receipts and expenditures 1942 (Box 6)
  - Reports of meetings 1942 (Box 6)
  - Newsletter, "Anti-Saloon League Speakers' Bulletin" 1919-1922 (Box 6)
  - Newsletter, "No-Repeal News" 1933 (Box 6)
  - Newsletter, "The League Workman" (Box 6)
  - Press releases, 8 folders (Box 6)
  - Treasurer's reports (Box 6)
  - Reports of Legal Department, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Reports on Temperance Legislation (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous minutes and reports, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Long Range Programs and special campaigns (Box 6)
  - Miscellanea, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - National Training School, Winona Lake, Indiana, 6 folders (Box 6)
- State Organizations
  - Anti-Saloon League of Illinois
    - Weekly reports of receipts and expenditures, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Reports of meetings (Box 6)
    - Subscription and solicitation reports (Box 6)
  - Iowa Anti-Saloon League
    - Legislative Bulletin (Box 6)
    - Superintendent's Annual reports (Box 6)
    - Resolutions (Box 6)
    - Press releases and statements (Box 6)
    - Printed material (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Anti-Saloon League of Minnesota
    - Annual reports and miscellanea (Box 6)
  - Anti-Saloon League of Kentucky Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Anti-Saloon League of Arkansas Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Wisconsin Anti-Saloon League Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Anti-Saloon League of Indiana (Box 6)
  - National Temperance League Reports and miscellaneous, 12 folders (Box 7)
  - Temperance League of Kentucky Correspondence (Box 7)
- Topical files
  - Names
    - Bale, Fred G (Box 7)
    - Bryan, William Jennings, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Cannon, (Bishop) James, Jr. (Box 7)
    - Capper, Arthur (Box 7)
    - Cunneen, John (Box 7)
    - Darrow, Clarence (Box 7)
    - Dickinson, Luren (Box 7)
    - Hammond, George (Box 7)
    - Johnson, "Pussyfoot" (Box 7)
    - McBride, F. Scott, 8 folders (Box 7)
    - Morris, Sam, 5 folders (Box 7)
    - National Temperance and Prohibition Council (Box 7)
    - National United Committee for Law Enforcement (Box 7)
    - Sheppard, Morris (Box 7)
    - Sottau, Henry J (Box 7)
    - Spence, Ben H (Box 7)
    - Sunday, Billy, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - York, Alvin (Box 7)
  - Subjects
    - Local option, 6 folders (Box 8)
    - Enforcement of 18th Amendment (Box 8)
    - Opposition to 18th Amendment, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Repeal of 18th Amendment, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Liquor advertising, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Sale of liquor on railroads (Box 8)
    - War-time prohibition (Box 8)
    - Prohibition of liquor sales around army camps (Box 8)
    - Olympian movement, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Catholics and the Presidency (Box 8)
    - Yale University Summer School Alcohol Studies, 10 folders (Box 8)
- Prohibition Dramatic Productions
  - "Prisoner at the Bar" (Box 8)
  - "Can the Law Be Enforced?", 3 folders (Box 8)
  - "Senator North's Deciding Vote", 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Dramatic Temperance debates, 7 folders (Box 9)
  - "Safety vs. Disaster" (Box 9)
  - Christgau-Pierre S. duPont debate, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - "Ten Nights in a Bar Room", 3 folders (Box 9)
  - "Protection", 1 folders; 1 volumes (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous, 5 folders (Box 9)
  - Posters and programs, 6 folders (Box 9)
- Miscellaneous
  - Miscellaneous, 11 folders (Box 9)
  - Printed material (Box 10)
- Scrapbooks /clippings
  - Clippings (loose), 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Scrapbooks, ca. 1910-1916, 2 volumes (Box 11)
  - Scrapbook concerning the National Convention of the Anti-Saloon League of America 1925 (Box 11)
  - Scrapbook concerning the enforcement of the 18th Amendment 1926 (Box 11)
  - Scrapbook concerning prohibition and Democratic politics 1926 (Box 11)
  - Scrapbook concerning the activities of the Anti-Saloon League of America 1926 (Box 12)
  - Scrapbook concerning prohibition and the election campaign 1928 (Box 12)
  - Scrapbook concerning the Southeastern States Prohibition Convention, St. Petersburg, Florida 1928 (Box 12)
  - Scrapbook concerning the Anti-Saloon League and the Senate Lobby investigation 1930 (Box 12)
  - Scrapbook concerning the repeal of the 18th Amendment 1932 (Box 12)
  - Scrapbook concerning prohibition and the enforcement of the 18th Amendment 1929-1932 (Volume 1)
  - Scrapbook concerning prohibition and the enforcement of the 18th Amendment 1931-1932 (Volume 2)
- Photographs
  - Personal Photographs (Box 13)
    - Individual Photographs (Box 13)
    - With groups (Box 13)
    - With William Jennings Bryan and others (Box 13)
  - Professional Photographs
    - Anti-Saloon League of Illinois, Staff Photographs 1923 (Box 13)
    - Anti-Saloon League of America, Washington, DC Headquarters (Box 13)
    - Anti-Saloon League of America, Washington D.C., Executive Committee 1932 (Box 13)
    - Winona Lake Training School, ca. 1944-1946 (Box 13)
  - Speakers and Activists Photographs
    - A-J (Box 13)
    - K-Z, and unidentified (Box 13)
    - Groups (Box 13)
  - Play and Movie Photographs
    - "Senator North's Deciding Vote," March 12, 1934 (Box 13)
    - "Ten Nights in a Barroom, play photographs (Box 13)
    - "Ten Nights in a Barroom," movie photographs (Box 13)
    - Play scenes, with Oscar G. Christgau (Box 13)
    - Play scenes, unidentified (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs
    - Sam Morris, speaking in Birmingham, Alabama April 20, 1941 (Box 13)
    - Brewery being dismantled and sent to China undated (Box 13)
  - Publicity Photos (Box 13)
  - Professional gatherings (Folder 1)
    (located in UAl)
- Sound recording
  - Radio address of Sam Morris, 1 phonograph records (Box 13)
    (located in phonograph disc collection)
Partial Index to Correspondence
Callahan, Patrick Henry, 1866-1940.
1931, 1933-1934, Nov. 12, 1935, Oct. 23, 1936, Feb. 18, 1937, Jan. 26, 1938
Cannon, James, 1864-1944.
1928, 1942-1944
Capper, Arthur, 1865-1951.
Dec. 31, 1931, Nov. 24, 1933 and Nov. 25, 1935
Dickinson, Luren Dudley, 1859-1943.
Dec. 22, 1938, Feb. 21, 1939 and Jan. 13, 1942
McBride, Francis Scott, 1872-1955.
Correspondence throughout
Rodeheaver, Homer A. (Homer Alvan), 1880-1955.
Dec. 28, 1935 and Jan. 8, 1943
Russell, Howard H. (Howard Hyde), 1855-1945.
Undated, Apr. 20, 1920, Dec. 8, 1925, Dec. 19, 1925, 1931, 1932, 1935, Feb. 16, 1938 and July 20, 1939
Sheppard, Morris, 1875-1941.
Aug. 16, 1918, Jan. 27, 1933, Sept. 12, 1933, Apr. 2, 1934 and Mar. 24, 1941
Sunday, Billy, 1862-1935.
Undated, 1935
Wallace, Clayton Morey, 1897-
1950, 1952-1957
York, Alvin Cullum, 1887-1964.
Nov. 20, 1931, 1932-1933, Apr. 5, 1934 and Oct. 21, 1944